[Music]
l
L say
[Music]
l
am
[Music]
and
l
l more
[Music]
so you have to know the whole story of
this song she wrote it on a Starbucks
bag off the internet but we had heard
lady Ruth sing it
you know before so uh we tricked her we
did a bait and
switch
uh like two days ago we said would you
come and teach us the words and the how
to do it correctly and and then she said
yeah I'll come on Thursday and then uh
like a couple hours ago we said and by
the way could you also
speak not funny
okay
[Laughter]
uh next time I take her class she's
gonna do something to me worse than
usual uh so anyway we've requested our
teacher uh lady Ruth she's my first
teacher my first yoga
teacher 100 years ago and uh you know
especially after last night it was so
pleasant to have Swami sash
shivananda uh uh teach and for me
especially to sit I like to sit and
listen to wise people speak because I
also have my own problems and I like to
hear you know my teachers speak to me
and uh
so uh lady Ruth has uh helped with the
foundation of Jiva mukti Yoga Center you
all know her and spent many years as a
close
disciple of uh guruji uh in uh
myor and uh many spent many years there
uh every year going and learning from
Shri Pabi Joyce and
um when she teaches yoga he comes
through her and it looks really funny as
a
lady uh but she's just like him very
tough and and uh she mispronounces
English numbers and you know like just
like him she's channeling him so uh you
know
I I think it's uh how do you
say I'm in the mood nowadays to hear
from people who are humble and who serve
people and uh who are kind and gentle
and uh follow their teachers guidance
yeah so uh mainly I just want to be
around her and listen to her say
something so anyway uh without further
Ado lady Ruth
[Applause]
laow
thank you thank you
everyone well he's not
kidding
with all what he just said about the
couple hours ago getting a
call but I was thinking
um recently because I've been
teaching for 20 years and or a little
bit longer even and I I always prepare
I'm always
prepared and
and So lately I've been thinking
that like there's a nervousness around
preparing and you know making sure that
I have the time set
aside to
prepare and um you know my husband
always says like I'm always
preparing and So lately I've been
thinking that it should be that you know
as certain point maybe I could prepare
less and that then maybe more of what I
knew could come through that somehow the
preparing is holding me back a little
bit was just a feeling that I had been
having
lately and so I thought I should prepare
a little less and try to you know but
then how do you do that if you're so
used to
Preparing how do you make that switch so
I had not made that
switch
but I had been thinking about it and
then I got the call today and I thought
that it would be bad karma if I said no
you know that I'm not prepared that I I
I I need a little more time you know
because also I had dinner planned so I
really only had 20 minutes you
know and um so I agreed you know in the
hopes that
um you know this thing about preparing
ing that we all go through I think it's
good we don't want to waste each other's
time
and you know we we respect each other
and so we want to prepare but I I think
sometimes all of us here in this room
have had and have great teachers and are
sincere about our our studies and our
practices and so we are prepared you
know and so anyway with with that said
let's
see let's see so um anyway gisha wanted
me to speak about the claas and
um well they they come in book two of
the yoga Sutra although they're
introduced in book one because iswar is
described as being clesa Karma vipaka
Sher upera untouched iswar doesn't have
these claas that I'm about to to to list
the enlightened being is free is
untainted is untouched is unharassed is
unbothered but everyone else has these
um these
clas um and klish means um to bother and
it's it's to be bothered
intensely but it's you who's bothering
yourself it's not
someone outside of you that's bothering
you so it's it's you're feeling harassed
and
um made tired and um
diminished and um
covered and it's you who's doing it to
yourself and um those are the that's
clich is to harass or torment or bother
and it's coming from you who doing it to
yourself you're bothering
yourself that's um CLA and um there are
five Puna five and um the first one is
aidia and
um aidia is ignorance Vidia is
knowledge um to be wise to be uh learned
and um vid
uh actually is um a small bell it has
many uh means many things but one thing
like when you get through all the words
what it means in the dictionary like in
as a tangent it says like a small bell
which is kind of interesting because
probably in a lot of religions but um in
India whenever there's a Puja there's a
bell ringing you know there's a lot of
like Bells bell ringing and if you're
looking for the Puja and you're lost and
you're not quite sure where it is you
might often hear a bell ringing and then
you know oh the Puja you're you're going
in the right direction so it's vid is
that knowledge that um you feel you're
going in the right
direction it's a relief you want to be
like hearing a bell you you you want to
go where it is a viia is not having that
is against that it's ignorance to be
against um knowledge it's uh
and
um
well I'm going to explain it a little
differently then you
know I believe that in in gisha
Tradition it would be explained
something like you think things are
coming at
you when instead they're coming from you
that that would be seen as aidia which
is
ignorance
um and that's that's a
beautiful
um that's
um the way I was have
been is um
aidia it's like um if you have something
gold and um like my Guru he loved gold
if you brought him a gift he was always
like is it
gold and he had like gold takes many
forms you know he had a he had all
different kinds of gold rings and he had
a gold coin and he had a gold uh chain A
thick one then he had a thin one then he
had a mediumsized one he had gold
bracelets and all the grandchildren had
little gold Tiaras and so gold it has
all these different forms
gold but um you can always take it and
they'll melt it and then they'll make
something
else out of it right it's gold is
pure so the essence of the gold
doesn't change even though it's a its uh
form keeps
changing so you could have a ring and
then it could be a brooch and then it
could be a necklace and it could be
thick or it could be thin or it could be
fragile or it could be all these
different forms and you could call it by
many different names but its
Essence would always be
gold and um that's viya that's not
that's
knowledge the spiritual knowledge that's
the knowledge of
gold the spiritual
knowledge which we would say is
Vidya is to understand that the same is
true of of all sensient
beings that um we're we're the
same we're of the same essence
and that it's through name and
form which is incredibly
varied that we can realize
this and if you're not interested in
that that's a
Vidya
so I don't think I'm totally off the
deep end here
because I've seen several times the Dal
Lama
speak and um as I'm I'm sure all of you
have heard him speak many more times
than I have but I have a few times heard
him speak to very different audiences
because I heard him speak in B La Coupe
and I heard him speak in New York City
and I heard him speak in
darala and um each time I heard him
speak he said the same thing when he
started which was that he said uh I I
come to
you not as Dal
Lama not as a
monk man in
robes not as um
Refugee man in
Exile or um not as um a
politici and he named you know many
different like significant things what
we would think of the Dal Lama specific
to his name and his
form and he and he said I I don't come
before you in in as any of
those
but I I come before
you as I'm the same I'm the same as
you and being of course that he's
enlightened when you hear that and
you're in his
presence it comes as a great relief you
know like everyone you could feel like a
wave of
reassurance oh he he's the
same you know so that's my understanding
of of Vidia is that
um you know we are we are one we are the
same if you take uh like if I take this
one and
I I divide
it into
many see I've I've divided it into three
we can
say that I've I don't have three
different things I have
one divided in
three so we are that's why they scui
always said God is one God is one God is
one we were like well but we see so many
you know he was like yes but God is one
you know so it's it's that idea that um
in essence things are always
changing for better and For
Worse
constantly procity motion movement
change nature
qualities but there is something Beyond
qualities Beyond change pure
untainted as it should
be
and knowing that to be who you
are is a
Vidya not knowing that is a
viya okay so
um like once some of you probably maybe
might have heard me tell this story few
of you know me well I was in H A Farm
Stand in um up near where I live and um
there was a man there buying peppers
like green Italian peppers and he had so
many of them in a
bag I thought well I wonder what he
would be doing with so many
peppers and uh so I said oh you know you
have a lot of peppers there what what
are you going to do he said oh I'm going
to pickle them I oh you know you're
going to pickle them was interesting to
me I like um pickle pickled fermented
food and everything oh you know I said
how do you do that so we got into this
conversation about how you pickle
peppers and um then he then he turned
and he said to me he said but you know
he said um I said well it looks like
you're making a lot he said no he said
not really he said I used to make a lot
when my wife was
alive and it was like I thought was
going to cry like there was something
like the moment that he said it it was
like I knew everything about this man
somehow like in that right so that's
Vidya it's it it's not something really
to
learn but it's all around us all the
time it's like truth when it's when you
feel that you're in the contact with the
truth there's nothing to
analyze
it's not difficult to understand it
doesn't belong to any particular group
of
people it's everywhere it's all around
us if when you're like you're present in
that
moment you know then another time maybe
somebody would say well I used to do a
um a lot before when my wife was alive
and you know you're like oh and it
doesn't you're you're not um though the
truth is all around us if you're not
present to
it then that's aidia you're under the
influence of
aidia when you put an uh in front of a
word it negates
it
um so my my mother was in the car and
she's 85 and um she she it's not good
for her to drive Willie she tries to
minimize her driving but she had some
errands that she wanted to do and um so
she decided to get in the car and do her
errands and she was going to go to the
bank that was the thing she wanted to
do so she was in the car she was driving
to the bank she's 85 and um there was
some music on the radio
and um she was very much enjoying
listening to the beautiful piece of it
was like a symphony and it was beautiful
and she was loving
it she got to the bank and the symphony
wasn't over yet and um so she she sat
there in the parking lot and um she
listened to the whole
Symphony and the Bank
closed
and cuzz the next day she she was like
she had to go to the bank and I was like
I thought you were going to go yesterday
so you know so she told me what happened
you know but she said but she said you
know I I had to hear it to its end and
then she said um I had to know who who
it was whose Symphony it was it was
Hector buros turned
out and
um so it was like she had to
know you know I'm sure it's happened to
all of us where we're in the car and
we're hearing something very beautiful
but we got to
go you know and for her like to make a
trip it's like it's a pretty big ordeal
at her
age but she had to CU she loves
classical music like classical music is
like God to her because it is I mean
that's where does that music come from
right so it's like she was glued to that
that's vid it's like you need to know
you're not going anywhere it's what
keeps you like on your meditation
cushion okay so that's um aidia so shall
I go on or is it
like we can we can cruise through the
other four because a viia is the main is
the main
one
okay so if I'm under the influence of a
Vidia then names and
forms
others and how they're different from
me is what I'm under the influence of so
that's called
asmita which gets translated as
egoism if I'm not ident identifying with
like when the Dal Lama says you know I I
come before you I'm the same well if I'm
not if that's not how I see myself then
I see myself as
other so then I'm going to build that
up into
something to be proud of right that's
asita that's
ego
so
um well my my very very dear friend Lisa
shrimp was uh lecturing a little while
ago and um and I was I had come to the
lecture and I was sitting in the group
and um she she started to quote the
Bhagavad Gita there was a verse in the
Bhagavad Gita that she she thought of
and she was talking about it and she
said um I I think it's from chapter 10
she said and then she said the verse and
then she saidoh she said but Ruth is
here Ruth will know which verse Which
chapter it's from and I was sitting over
there and everybody turned and oh Ruth
will
know and then um I said um because at
the time I thought I said well I think
it's chapter six and So Lisa said oh
well definitely chapter 6 you know for
sure it's chapter 6 then all of a sudden
I was like gosh I don't you maybe it's
really chapter 10 you know I'm not
sure but she thought for sure that it
would have been chapter 6 if that's what
I thought so then after the lecture we
went back to where she was
staying and of course right away I was
like I want to do they have a babad g
you know and of course they did it just
seems like no matter where I go there's
a babad
Gita so in no time at all we had located
to babad Gita and um we I went looking
for the
verse and it was in chapter 10 it was in
the chapter that she had said that it
was
in and I said look Lisa I said um you
know you were right all along it it
wasn't in uh chapter 10 and Lisa said oh
she said um I thought for sure if you
said it it was in chapter 6 it would be
in chapter
6 and then Lisa said and Lisa's like
she's been doing her sodna for a long
time she's she's the real deal Lisa said
um isn't it great when you really think
that someone else knows more than you do
she was like isn't that so
great so that's like the opposite of
osita you know and it's like we get we
get to go deep into that
it's such a beautiful thing you know we
don't have to put on
airs we don't have to be
right if you ever have the feeling like
um
because I don't know why but often it
seems like I get singled out at like
events like you know gurji used to do
this to me and he he'd say like what
about you know like well Ruth and people
would be like well why her you know and
uh you know but he would do that he
would like single me
out and it's like there was a period
where I would get singled out and I I
could feel a kind of like Pride like I
would that's me you know that they're
talking about you know and I would feel
it and I would I would kind of you
know and um and now it's
like you know I'm just much more free of
that and it's such a relief you know
it's it's um it's hard to keep that up
it's hard to keep the you know what when
you build yourself up then you got to
maintain that it's so much
easier to just kind of let it go you
know so and then but then because the
tendency to have an ego of course is so
great and Dee rooted in all of us but
then sometimes even when you least
expect it and you feel like yeah you've
youve you've worked that one out it it
comes back you know and then all of a
sudden you maybe you feel like oh my God
I'm like I'm gloating you know and you
can feel it you know and because you're
not used to it you feel it even more
like it's and then you have this sense
like H this is just not what I want to
be doing this is not interesting to me
you know it's like you still have a seed
to have an a big
ego but as soon as it's
like fruition coming into fruition
you're you're for sure clear that this
is
not this is a base base is
interesting because
um like the lowest chakra is like at the
base of the
spine then when we say like bass
Behavior it's kind of like of course you
play the bass so you have to be and
that's the most beautiful instrument and
I love it when you play the bass so I
think maybe I'll stay away
from okay then um the next
claa is um is rager oh
rager and um Raga means craving it's of
course if I have a big ego I'm going to
want things right it's like that when
you're under the influence of your
ego then it's never
ending the ego just wants that's what
the ego does it wants and so
if you were to stop and examine your
mind at like any given moment at all at
any time you'd be wanting something you
know like whether it was a sip of
water you know or but you're just your
mind
is driven in this way where you're just
always wanting
something and um that that keeps you
from it's like when you meet somebody
who's going to pickle peppers and his
his wife has passed
away if you just want something then if
he says something really beautiful or if
you feel like God is speaking to you
through this man you might miss it
because you're you're just thinking
about you know what you
want it keeps us small you know when
we're and um preoccupied with whatever
it is that we
want there's a verse in the Bhagavad
Gita I don't know which chapter it is uh
but it says something like
um
God will take care of the ones who don't
take care of
themselves
it's a beautiful it's beautiful so
meaning
that if you're if you're not looking
after yourself that's not the one you're
looking after
you then God will look after you but
then the next verse is something
like but only if it's you're really not
looking after you you know so if if
you're like well 60 40 70 30 80
20% like 80% it's not about me but 20%
it is then you're you're you've got the
claas like it would only be if you when
you reach that point where 100% you're
like your life is for
others oh Dolly llama you forgot to eat
today oh I hadn't thought about it oh um
Dolly Lama your your robes are um torn
you you don't you need a new get a new
set sometimes oh I I I I had not
realized I did not
know you know like there are people like
that they don't think of
themselves that's the opposite of um
asmita the those people are free those
people are
happy those people are very good
teachers
DEA DEA is when you hate
everything like everything like it's too
hot and it's um too crowded and it's too
polluted and um it's too spicy and it's
too fried and
um it's just you know something is
bothering you and then you go around the
corner and something else is bothering
you and you go around the corner and
like something else is bothering you and
it's just like everyone bothers you
everyone bothers you everyone is a big
disappointment you hate everyone
but it's coming from within
you the problem keeps appearing on every
corner but it's something inside of
yourself that you don't like that's
being
mirrored that's a
DEA and um the last one is um abini
Vasa
uh which gets translated as fear of
death and if you break down the word
exactly how it gets translated into fear
of death would be
something to talk about at another point
because Vasa ni
ABI um
but I live I live in the country you'll
have to come sometime and see where I
live it's very um it's very wonderful
where I
live and um we have a pond and um we
have um a lot of wild animals and
um often when I go walking I'll come
across a bunny rabbit or a bear or
um a duck or a coyote we have many many
different animals and um when I see the
animal I'll I'll say hello to the animal
like if there's a goose I'll say oh
hello
goose and the
Goose you can tell will wonder whether
or not like the first thing that comes
into the Goose's
mind is am I going to hurt
them you know you can
tell and then now we've lived in the
same place for some time now they know
like they come they know that I'm we
like having
them so the
abesa all every animal every human being
everyone has it you can see if you ever
try to
kill any sensient being they will try to
avoid
that it's
inherent that we want to
live
and um that's that's a beautiful thing
that we want to
live
but I guess it can become a source of
Torment
so those are um those are all ways in
which we
um we we worry ourselves to the point
where we're
miserable but I I should end on apolog
of note I don't want to don't want to
end with the word miserable Well yoga
yoga is there to
um yoga is there yoga and meditation is
is there to remove those
clas which act as
obstructions to our our true
nature and um there's a beautiful Sutra
pratia he sukma that comes after all the
the description of the
clas how to get rid of these claas and
the and the word is used prati prasa
which means to go
back and then there's a lot of different
thoughts as to you know what that means
and how it's a chain and all of that
but I I like to think of it as
um
if you ever have the feeling that
um something didn't go so
well and
um then you can always go
back cuz pra is to go forward T is to go
back PR is to go forward prti pra and
Sava is actually the honey on the inside
of a a
flower so it's this idea like well if it
didn't didn't go right the first time
maybe you could go back and then you
could go forward again of course
infinite examples are
there but just the other
night I was here in New York City I was
rushing to catch my bus I ran into a um
very dear friend she seemed very upset
she had gotten some very bad
news and I said uh well is somebody
going to take you home and she was with
somebody and she said yeah you know he
he'll take me home and I said okay and I
said well I'm going to go catch my bus
and then I was going to catch my bus and
I was thinking um well maybe I should go
back maybe I she would want to have
somebody sleep with her because I knew
she was by
herself and I thought maybe she'd like
to have some company so I'll and then I
thought oh but you know you're going to
miss your
bus and that's procity like we're it's
that's death it's like we're we we're in
motion and we can't you know you feel
that time is devouring you know and you
you can't get out from it and
um and it's
miserable then you have a moment that
kind of cuts through all that and you're
like maybe I should go back you know
maybe I should just forget about my bus
and for just forget about time and this
is this is different like she seemed
very very upset and so
um then you know then the minute you
think well I should go back then you
think nah I should go forward and then I
was like prati prasa that's why that's
swadaya you know when you study and then
these things actually come to your
mind
you know and then you and then you act
upon them and then you know what these
things are until you actually act upon
them you know you really don't know much
I mean that's what my Guru used to say
anyway
um so then you you you can always go
back so any of those things that are
that are um bothering you you know it's
like just the idea of tracing
yourself back tracing yourself back you
know there's a beautiful poem by a a
writer that I like a lot named Susan
minow and she um she talks about
um get well she's had a fair amount of
success and
[Music]
um I guess that she was missing she felt
like she had a lot of this success that
kind of built up her
ego and then one night she got she was
staying in London and she was in a flat
and she got locked out of her um
apartment and it was like late at night
and she got dropped off and it was like
3:00 a.m. cuz that's the name of the
poem actually 3:00 a.m. and she realized
that she didn't have the um the key and
she couldn't get in and she was like in
a strange city strange to her and um so
there was like some scaffolding and so
she started like climbing up the
scaffolding to see if like maybe she
could get in through like this
scaffolding and she realized that when
while she was climbing up the
scaffolding trying to see if there would
be like a way that she could get in that
she felt
herself you know she felt something of
of who she was that the ease of
everything and the success had kind of
like covered this feeling of like who
she really was and that somehow
scrambling to get in at like 3:00 a.m.
and find a like window that she could
like break into her own place helped her
to reconnect to you
know her
her her Deeper
Self so that is the then you won't be
craving things and then you won't be
hating things and then you won't be
afraid of things because all what you'll
have is within you that's a a better um
a better way to end so I'm sorry I took
up so much of your time I'm a bit slow
and long- winded and everything but
that's just a a you know um sutras are
there and and um it's it's good because
then when you when they're acting on you
when they're influencing you sometimes
it's helpful oh you know this is the
influence of of aidia you know like and
then you
can stop the um patterns of behavior
that are making you miserable and and
you can stop them and
um then that's where all the all
the things that you learn from gishi
Michael you know uh are the same as as
what this
is thank you so
[Applause]
much
yeah give it to
Lisa no one more
Lisa thank
you
okay hi uh thank you lady
Ruth
um okay so we'll just go straight into
it
um I'd like to speak about another place
for Nirvana another context in which we
can learn more about the idea of Nirvana
um and those are countless I mean what
we've done in the three days is
uh something like 10% of what we could
do and I don't know how we're going to
do more we'll see okay some people get
to go to the Bahamas and we'll do more
there all right but even then it won't
be done so maybe someday we do more okay
uh but another idea about Nirvana which
is in your reading today is called the
four fruits of virtue or of goodness
okay so uh Good Karma uh doing good
karma uh projects you through four
stages in your life okay and we'll just
we won't talk long about that uh this is
a basic idea of
Buddhism and we talked about it some
yesterday
uh my llama he used to uh you know make
great demands of me I was working all
the time and
uh especially stuff I didn't want to do
like construction and stuff like that so
you
know then we built his house I had to
build his house and then I had to you
know every week there was some new thing
I had to do I had to learn learn how to
take apart his car and put it back
together
and you know so anyway one day he
decided he needed a uh path from the
doorway to the to the driveway and I
don't know it was like how long like
30 30 ft or something you know so we you
know we dug out a path and then we put
gravel in it he said I don't like the
gravel he used to do this a lot you'd
buy gravel he'd say I don't like gravel
then you have to take it back to the
store try to get the money back you know
and then you'd buy him colored gravel he
said I don't like colored gravel you're
lazy you know and then
uh then we got him expensive uh slate
flag Stones you know these must be okay
and uh we we had to we started from the
house and we made it to the driveway it
took like two or three days and we had
to lay them down dig them dig out the
grass put in sand and then you lay them
down on the sand and then they're they
jiggle and then you have to take them
off again and it was a big hustle and uh
so but it was this experience of you
would finish one slate stone and then
you would put you'd step on it and then
you'd put the next one down and then
somewhere in the three days I figured
out what he was trying to teach me every
time there was some kind of lesson
right and uh it's this
thing
uh when you walk through a
room it looks like all the things are
stationary and you are uh moving through
a stationary room right uh but actually
what's happening is that your mind is uh
laying down the next uh thing you see as
you go when you are reading a a novel
and you turn Turn the Page in this in
this system we believe the next page is
empty when you reach to turn the page
the next page has nothing on it and then
your mind lays the words down okay or
when you see a movie your mind is
creating the next scene if you don't
like the way the last movie you saw
ended it's your fault okay all right now
it's very interesting you know it's very
interesting idea uh that you are laying
down reality As you move you know you
know and reality is not going anywhere
you're just laying down new Stones you
know so
uh as
you use your knowledge of where reality
is coming from to reduce your negative
emotions right and just to uh review why
we're here these three days it's Nirvana
immersion uh Nirvana is the final
destruction of Cl
the
permanent uh destruction of your
glacious uh and we took six right we
took six uh popular ones everybody voted
for the one they had the most minus
jealousy you know it was pretty even
right the vote was pretty even uh we
have jealousy we have anger we have
addictions we have judging other people
we have busyness and we have
procrastination so we had to vote who
what's their main one and it was pretty
equal uh so Nirvana is defined as the
destruction of those things by the end
of tonight
hopefully we can be given a program that
we can follow to destroy our own worst
emotion our own most negative Emotion by
the end of tonight gashi Michael should
have faced his job
Jey uh should have thought about how it
comes in his mind and then he should
have a program how to destroy it right
by the end of tonight you will have that
[Music]
okay so the destruction of glaas in this
system depends on how well you
understand what's going on around you
where things come from so avidya is the
root of DEA and Raga and then if you
destroy a viida
then they won't have a place to stand so
in the scriptures is described your
progress through the destruction of a
Vidya and in the Buddhist scriptures and
in the yoga Sutra it's mentioned you you
work on the most obvious forms of
jealousy first you know where you
actually walked over to the I've had my
students do this you know one of them is
serving me dinner and the other one gets
jealous and walks over and takes the
tray out of their hand physically
and then turns and give it to me as if
it's going to please me you know and uh
you know so that's like a very gross
obvious form of jealousy or Envy uh and
then as you walk through the as you work
through the
claas uh and your ignorance becomes less
and less so as you're viia as your
knowledge
increases uh your claas decrease and
they have nine stages there's the you
know big jealousy then medium jealousy
then subtle jealousy then each of those
has big and medium and subtle so the
last one you get rid of is your subtle
form of your subtle jealousy and that
would be like I don't
know you see a stranger on the street
and you look down at their shoe and it
looks a little better than yours and
then you glance
away and it it's strikes you for a
moment you have a moment recognition
that their Sho that side of their shoe
is more beautiful than that side on your
shoe that would be like subtle
subtle
okay and you move through them as your
uh tendency towards a
Vidya uh is is destroyed okay it's all
based on a Vidya to get over the way the
back of the other person's shoe looks
you have to destroy your most subtle of
VI so viia goes down in nine stages also
like
that as far as rebirth certain things
happen as you decrease your avidya as
you decrease your misunderstanding of
Life your rebirths change okay uh and
that's called the four fruits uh of of
The Virtuous
way they start with the direct
perception of emptiness okay okay so you
got
to work for a few billion years to just
get to the first one okay all right they
start with the direct presumption
emptiness and in this system of four
stages in your spiritual career that's
called entering the stream gupa it means
uh stream enterer it's called someone
who has entered this stream when you see
emptiness
directly whether or not you have bodh
whether or not you're bodh right uh you
reach what's called gupa or entering the
stream I
I Envision it or I see it as a a
conveyor belt and uh someone drops you
on a conveyor belt the moment you see
emptiness directly they say that until
the day you see Ultimate Reality
directly no one not even a Buddha can
predict when you will get enlightened
it's it's still on the edges of
possibility right it's going to happen
but they can't say what year what day
okay when you see emptiness directly
then then then it's set and you you will
never go back you can't fail after that
and and within a short time seven
lifetimes you will become enlightened
okay if you can do it if if you can see
emptiness directly within seven
lifetimes you will become enlightened
and you see that when you see emptiness
directly you see the seven life
times which is the longest possible
right
uh so that's called stream enter Then
you the progress the reason that they
can say you'll be out in a specific
amount of time is that seeing emptiness
directly damages your avidya irre
ably okay it can never go back to the
way it was before uh and then you start
to make more and more progress the next
stage is called uh once returner lenik
Chira it means to come back one more
time that means to the desire realm okay
so there are three Realms by tradition
of
existence uh we we live in the desire
realm do what do you call comma
something
kamu uh and the reason they call it the
desire realm first Dal Lama said is that
it is characterized by a fascination
with food and sex okay you walk you go
around New York New York is even more
wor it's worse than most places there's
girls and bikinis on every building like
it's weird I don't know why uh huge you
know 30 foot people in in the cold and
in bikinis and and uh it's because and
the internet is like that and fast food
is like that and people just have a
desire for those things so they're
there so we live in the desire realm uh
some of us have more desire for that
kind of thing some of us has left H have
less but we all have it to some extent
we all have it or you wouldn't be here
okay uh unless you're an emanation of
some holy being okay if you're a normal
person uh you're here because you have
some degree of those desires
okay I think it's good to know and to
admit it right then you can do something
with
it so there comes a time when your
understanding of where stuff is coming
from gets so
sophisticated that you can lay down the
next Stone
as a birth in this realm only one more
time so that second stage is called once
returner and after that you won't come
back to this realm okay which is
characterized by mortality death
suffering
okay if you work on your a Vidya more
then you become a a non- returner okay
uh that's the third one chonga in
tibetan you can't come back again to the
desire realm so where do you go you're
still in sansara you're still in a
suffering birth but you go to two Realms
called form realm or or formless realm
right rupu and I don't know
arupu uh and these are like uh Club Med
Realms okay they are
temporary uh they in the Buddhist
tradition they say big worldly deities
are living there like
Brahma you know and they they can move
planets they can boss around
whole planets of people and it's
temporary it only lasts for a
while but you can go to those Realms uh
if you work on your Avidia and as your
misunderstanding gets less and less you
can't lay down uh a stone which is a
desire around birth okay because birth
as we said yesterday is not a thing
where your spirit is floating after you
it leaves your body right they say 4
ounces and then uh your spirit leaves
your body and then uh there's a dog this
is lower Buddhist schools also there's a
dog uh a spirit being Bardo being can
travel through any physical substance
except their mother's
womb so then at some point they bump
into the skin of their mother's womb and
they get trapped the spirit gets trapped
and then they must be the mother becomes
pregnant at that time and then they they
must be born there that's lower
school higher School
says the world you see now is a stepping
stone that you have laid down by how
you've treated other people in your life
right and then uh the seeds to to see
your arm as a human wear
out because every hour that you spend
with an arm you are wearing out the
karmas that created that arm right and
sooner it's a debit card you're born
with a debit card and it wears out it
always wears up and then and then the
seeds to see this as a human arm will
wear out then the seeds behind those
seeds will come to the front of the
Q and they could be dog seeds
then
then the thing that your karmic seeds
were making you see as an
arm then your karmic seeds make you see
that same thing that same cylinder as a
leg and a paw and then you is a dog okay
so in the higher schools it's not that
you die and your spirit goes someplace
else and leaves your body and goes to
another body it's not like that you are
setting down Stepping Stones
and it's just the next Stone and the the
Paw is coming from the same mind that
created the hand but the seeds wore out
okay that's all it's and then that's
frightening that means by the way when
those seeds wear out for an arm or a
hand the seeds wear out to think of
yourself as a
human 5 minutes after the seeds wear out
for human arm
you can't remember that you were ever
human because the seeds to remember you
were human wear out when the siege to
see it as a hand wear out so you just
think you're a dog and then you is a dog
okay it's very frightening it's not that
your car has to hit you you know you
could put somebody in a bank vault I
think of the one there's one on Fifth
Avenue around 43rd Street I used to walk
by it every day because our office was
on 45th Street there's a huge Bank fault
you look through the window and there's
on the way to the public
library to read the conier during your
lunch hour and uh there's a huge Vault
and I I you could put somebody in there
and you could lock the door and you
could have them do Asus every day and
eat organic food and take chia seeds and
uh still the seeds would wear out they
would still die you you know they would
still Agee and die at pretty much the
same rate okay and uh it's just the
seeds wearing
out so when you get to Arad that's the
fourth of the stages okay all the SE all
the
ignorance is
gone and
then as it says in the yoga sura fourth
chapter right
Karm the the
uh the lack of a VI destroys
the virility of the seeds the seeds
cannot produce a result there's a debate
in Buddhism I think they pretty much
decide the seeds are still there the
vasanas are still there and the
sanskaras are still there but they can
never grow because there's no ignorance
okay then you're in arat then you've
reached nirvana okay and you cannot take
even a birth in one of the form realm or
the formless realm
okay do you just disappear no because
you have three kinds of seeds uh a
Shukla aknam a yogi we you don't have
white dirty karmic seeds anymore and you
don't have black dirty karmic seeds
anymore to produce temporary Pleasures
or temporary pains all you have is seeds
that were collected with knowledge
consciously which we're going to talk
about by the end end of the evening
because I'm going to teach you how to
collect a seed consciously to remove
whatever your favorite claa is okay
that's sexy all right so by the end of
the night you will learn how to plant a
pure
seed and and destroy your favorite
negative emotion and it always works
okay it's very beautiful okay
so and our heart has reached that stage
they have seeds ripening which are pure
seeds they will have a body of light
what they call Diamond tee body in
V but what they call it the yoga there
something there
uh that's also close but that's there's
another line anyway uh you will have a
diamondlike body and
uh and then you will emanate to
countless planets okay that's Arad I
wanted to talk about the word AR okay
arhat means a person who has achieved
Nirvana so you should know the word okay
you're trying to get to be an
arhat uh anybody who achieves Nirvana is
an arat there's two ways to read the
word uh one is Ari Hut okay Ari Hut Ari
means an
enemy okay and Hut means to to to hit or
to
strike uh sometimes the root is Hun and
we said before that you see that word in
ainsa it becomes an i or in the English
word gun is a
cognate uh so arut means to destroy the
enemy the enemy is
what your own negative emotions okay we
want to make you a arut about one of
your negativities by by the end of
tonight
okay did you get any feeling for what it
would be like not to have it during
these three days did you play with that
I don't know I did I was thinking what
if I was never jealous last night I
didn't feel jealousy about Swami G you
know he plays really good music and he
speaks very well and I was just enjoying
him and then I was thinking what if I
always enjoyed talented people you know
I had a taste a little taste what would
it be like not to have your favorite
negative emotion I hope you got some
feeling what would be like half of your
sadness would go away half of your
unhappiness would go away if you just
took out one of them your day would be
twice as happy you'd be twice as happy
that's pretty cool we'll try to do it by
the end of tonight okay no kidding
uh then the other way to take that word
is there's a root
called a r h and uh it means to be
deserving or to be
worthy and uh so a lot of
times in the Tibetan scriptures which
are translations from Sanskrit you will
see a sentence that says our hearts are
called AR Hearts because they are worthy
of offering uh you can make a lot of
good karma by offering something to an
Arad uh because they are they are
deserving of offerings but the Tibetan
ancient translators chose the to
translate arat so in tibetan the word
for an Arad is DBA say da chba daba
enemy Destroyer so the translators took
it as Ari Hut but still the sutras that
were translated say they are
worthy you know they are called are hot
because they are worthy but in tibetan
it comes out they are enemy destroyers
because they are worthy and you lose it
so it's one of the few places where you
lose the meaning of the Sanskrit in
tibetan uh so those are the four fruits
you sto laying down the stones okay I
don't talk much about it because Western
people aren't much worried about dying
or what's going to happen to them
afterwards because they're so caught up
in their Facebook and
stuff seriously like you know
anyway uh
then that brings that brings the author
of our text or what I wrote for you to a
question is it possible to reach nirvana
and fall
back okay like that's a good question
right is it possible that you could stop
your claas and then something bad
happens and they come back can they come
back after you reach nirvana and we say
no okay okay but I think you should know
why because you know Buddhism is always
saying everything is impermanent right
and everything is Ana Everything Changes
right so it's important for a Buddhist
to explain why Nirvana is
permanent uh because we generally say
nothing is permanent so you have to
understand
why uh when you reach nirvana you will
always stay there you can never fall
back okay
why
let's say you have anger let's say anger
is your problem right and you have
somebody in your life who normally
criticizes you or attacks you most of us
have
somebody uh who criticizes us right
unwantedly
um and then you feel angry about them
right you feel anger at the person in
your life who criticizes you regularly
okay Swami G yesterday what do he say
about criticism
yeah is the one thing that nobody likes
uh some Swami shivanand said something
about that
uh so try to imagine the person you know
in your life who criticizes you right
now think of somebody who who criticizes
you get that get them in
mind I think as your karma gets better
there's fewer people to think of but
there's always
somebody then in this system uh the way
to stop your anger at the person who
criticizes you is to reflect that they
are criticizing you because a karmic
seed is opening in your
mind and that seed was planted when you
were critical of someone else last week
last month okay every person whoever
criticized you in your life life was
flowing from
you from you being from you criticizing
someone else by the way it doesn't have
to be the same person okay you can
criticize somebody at work and come home
and your husband will criticize you okay
why because the karma is carried in your
mind it's not like Karma respects the
difference between your office and your
home okay people used to come to me I'm
quitting the company you I say why and
they say I have a lousy super supervisor
you know and I'd say okay call me after
6 months let me know how it's going you
know and they're they'd call me after 6
months and they'd say I have a lousy
supervisor at my new company you know
you carry your karmas with you you see
it doesn't help to run away from things
uh so
anyway at some point you realize when
your husband criticizes you that it's
because you planted a seed at work by
criticizing somebody else right um
then we have to talk
about the
perception that your husband made a
decision to criticize you okay got
it in this system did your husband make
a decision to criticize you no he he's
not acting on his own accord or or
through his will he is in comp compell
to criticize you because of seeds in
your mind okay you he doesn't have a
choice to criticize you therefore it
doesn't help to try to talk to him and
it also doesn't help to try to not talk
to him cuz it's not his problem and he
doesn't have a choice and that's why it
doesn't always work when you reason with
him and it doesn't always work when you
do the I learned this thing that I do I
learned the name for
it passive uh aggression
or is that what it
is my yeah no my mom taught me that I I
realized that cuz they got divorced my
parents got divorced and she never
criticized my dad but there was this
she'd say yeah we don't have any food
this week you know he didn't send the
alimony but he's a nice guy you know and
then you're you're like and then I
picked that up from her you know and I
don't criticize people I don't get angry
but I I say something like you know yeah
they're a nice person and maybe they'll
pay the retreat money next week you know
something like that
uh so it doesn't help to be passive
aggressive and it also doesn't help to
be
aggressive uh neither one works because
they don't work all the time if if they
were a cause they would work all the
time okay now question for you
the husband that you get upset
at is the one who has power to decide
whether to criticize you or not am I
right you get angry at your
husband because he decided to criticize
you am I right if if if you found out
there was a Arab terrorist in the closet
who told him he would shoot him if he
didn't criticize you you wouldn't blame
your husband right I mean you you blame
him because you think he made a decision
to criticize you and that if you were
persuasive enough he would not criticize
you you believe that right in this
system follow me keep stay with me okay
this is going to just decide whether
Nirvana lasts or not
ready is there a husband in your house
who decided to criticize you does he
exist no such husband exists can we say
that in tibetan terms it's gcha right uh
so can we say that anytime you're upset
with somebody you're upset at someone
who was never
there can we say that yeah that's the
point and that's your only hope for
Nirvana that's your only hope for
Nirvana okay if if he was a person who
who was who could decide to criticize
you or decide to stop criticizing you
it's hopeless it's hopeless okay the
point is all the people you ever got
upset at were never
there
okay once you see that you can't go back
the better you get at recognizing that
you can't go back okay it's the snake
and the Rope thing you know I have a
water hose outside my on my porch I've
mistaken it for a snake once and then
you know I stepped on it and went Squish
and it didn't
go and then you know and now I just
don't think of it as
a I cannot think of it as a snake
anymore okay it's not possible to go
back once you realize that you were
getting a
upset at people who were never there you
can't go back if Nirvana were anything
else if if anger management was the way
then you're in trouble okay then you can
slide again you can have an addiction
again you see what I mean you can
slide out of a problem that you have C
that you have cured with bandaids you
see what I mean but once you realize
that the coffee you wanted was was never
there the coffee you fought to
get was never there then you you won't
have that addiction you can't go back to
wanting it you see what I mean it's not
possible Nirvana is permanent okay the
the final evolution of this kind of
thinging is permanent you never go back
you can't go back what you going to go
back into your house and decide the
husband is coming from himself again you
see the Rope the the garden hose is his
name
you know after 2 years of seeing that it
wasn't a snake you don't go back okay
because the thing was never there and
once you get it then you never slide
back again it's not possible it has to
do okay I'm going to throw this at you
and I'm not going to stay there it has
to do with the idea of negation okay it
has to do with the idea of
negation and it's similar to the idea of
emptiness okay it is the idea of
emptiness here we
go empty is unchanging it's one of the
few unchanging things in the
universe my uh deadly enemy my fellow
student art Engle whose Tibetan was
better than
me it upsets me just to think about him
uh one day he raised he kept
interrupting the Llama which was really
bad when I did it it was intelligent
question and uh then he kept
interrupting Rach and one day he said
Rach you know R is in the middle of this
deep logic text and and art goes Rach r
you know and I'm like everybody's like
you know and then he's like are all
unchanging things negatives negations
absences and remember say yes damn you
figured that out and I'm
like you know and uh think about that
okay think about that okay the fact that
a husband who had some choice to
criticize you or not was never there is
an unchanging thing it will never be
more or less and it will never
vary he's either there or he's not there
he can't be half there or lady Ruth was
talking about 80
2730 he can't be partly there and he
will never be partly there either he's
coming from himself or he's coming from
you okay
that's
all he's 100% not there it's not like
he's ever going to be 80% not there he's
just not there got
it that's that's one of the reasons why
Nirvana is permanent and you have to
chew on that you have to think about
that okay it's like
emptiness I just leave you with that
maybe in a year we'll talk about it
again all
right
uh I'm going to I want to just introduce
to you the next idea and then we'll take
a short break okay but it's going to be
a short break probably you won't even be
able to go to the bathroom or you'll
have to come back
halfway
uh I'm GNA kind of skip to the end of
the Nirvana thing tonight because some
people can't go to the
Bahamas and uh there's a
thing about how our hearts see the world
that was always difficult for me I
always had trouble with with a certain
detail about Nirvana and it had to do
with if you reach our
heart does your husband ever seem to be
coming from his side got it okay if you
reach our
heart do you even ever perceive a
husband that you could get angry at or
is it just gone forever you see because
we say in Buddhism that part of the
problem of a Vidya is that the nature of
the world in which we live is that it
tricks you there's something about the
world which is
tricky okay coming this
way the the world is uh
tricky and is cheating you is deceiving
you and then whether you buy it or not
it's your problem okay things look to be
coming from their own side whether you
believe it or not is a matter of
training and meditation and yoga okay
so but then at some point your karma
gets so good that they don't even seem
to be coming from their own side and
that always confused me and I was never
sure at what point you overcome that
okay so one
day about a year ago I was trudging
through we have 8 million pages in the
database this John Brady's project is in
year 25 now they are still typing it's
3% finished they'll go for another 150
years okay kind of Mark your P has to
worry about funding it okay that's why
and okay and
uh and I found this beautiful text uh
from our Monastery from a llama in the
1600s his name was Kang R he did one of
the yoga series that you studied I think
it's the the four uh
immeasurables what do you call them
karuna we we have a yoga series based on
that that he designed in the 17th
century and we taught it to you guys uh
but he wrote a an
essay about
the question I just mentioned you know
do you ever stop does the world ever
stop looking
tricky and at what point do you stop
taking it as tricky okay and uh I I
found it I me and Ningbo were looking
for it in the car we do all our work in
the car driving up and back you know and
Brooks is careful to take the wrong
roads and stuff so we'll have more time
now just kidding
uh but it was like a miracle like I was
looking for that and I found it and so I
translated it in the car Nimbo converted
it into bton at Starbucks we uh emailed
it to Jennifer where are you Delorenzo
where is
she we we emailed it to her and she got
it printed before the class okay but I
want you to learn that I want to teach
it to you it's it's incredible and it
it's how it feels to reach nirvana how
does it feel to reach nirvana okay it's
just a three or four page piece but it's
it's really really beautiful and it will
serve you for the rest of your life I I
I it's a it's a very extraordinary Karma
that that we found it and it's so
beautiful so uh I have just one thing um
where's that single Dem the other
anybody have one it's in my backpack if
there's
yeah so uh we're changing the mood at
diamond mountain
university uh we used to have the
retreat teachings every in the coldest
week of the year and the hottest week of
the year and then we decided that was a
little dumb and uh so we're going to
switch it to Spring and
fall and uh we're going to have a new
format and uh instead of me or other
people talking for you know five days or
something we thought let the retreatant
talk for
themselves uh so we every six months
we'll choose five
retreatants and we'll blindfold them and
we'll lead them to the temple so we're
going to hold it in the temple we're
going to stretch the border of the
retreat to the
temple uh a because it has air
conditioning B because it's $2,000 to
put that t up and there's a ritual you
can do to extend the Border uh which is
what we did in the first three Retreat
so anyway you'll we'll be in the temple
it'll be a three-day weekend Friday
evening to Sunday afternoon Friday night
Saturday night and Sunday afternoon so
we're going to let you go home at 4: so
you can catch a flight and get back to
New York by Monday and we won't start
till Friday evening so you know you just
take work off or something and we three
two hours behind
you uh
anyway uh every night uh two or three of
the retreatants will speak uh
blindfolded for all the retreatants will
be there behind a screen and they'll all
they won't be able to see you you won't
be able to see them but they'll be air
conditioning for both and then
uh in the weekend five of the retreatant
will speak and share what's happening in
their head during this they're in for a
year and a half now so they will tell
you we ask them please tell us what it
feels like or what's your biggest
breakthrough that you had uh in deep
Retreat for 18 months so far we know
share it with us and wet our what do you
call our appetite then we'll want to do
more Retreats and you know and we're
going to try to facilitate that at
Diamond Mount we're going to build some
more cabins now uh for short-term
Retreats people who want to do a month
or a week and we have a goal to make it
uh what do you call it a pamper Retreat
like we're building Gardens and we're
we're changing the architecture to
Spanish classical like
alra we're going to make it what do you
call it a like an elegant place and in
elegant uh Gardens and and fountains and
and Retreat cabin quickly that you can
stay in for a week or a month and then
you get like really nice service and we
want to bring in single mothers from
South Phoenix who are stressed and we
have this thing called pampered Retreat
and prisoners we're serving a lot of
prisoners now and we want to be able to
when they come out they have a place to
go they can do a retreat they can get
their life together we have a lot of
prisoners now in our group so we want
them to we want that mount to be like a
really elegant place and uh where you
can have a like a really beautiful deep
retreat in a beautiful setting and sort
of a so
anyway uh we'll have five retreating
speaking and then between each Retreat
and there'll be someone who from their
graduating class that didn't go into
Retreat and is doing something good in
the world so I think what we're hoping
for is a Synergy the people who didn't
go in who are doing beautiful things in
the world maybe Cora will come up and
speak sometime right that would be nice
and then they will describe like she has
a project teaching children poor
children in the bario uh yoga in Buenos
Ares so you would talk about that and
your experiences and then in between we
would hear from people who have been in
deep Retreat because I want to marry
them you see I want us to be both I I
want them to hear about beautiful ways
of serving people when they get out and
I want you to think about going in you
see I I mean and I I don't think it's 3
years is so necessary I think uh it
could be a month it could be two months
it could be a week so we're going to try
to build new we have two more valleys
there that we
own and they're empty and I would like
to build some short-term Retreat cabins
that are very comfortable and beautiful
and and have Gardens and things like
that so that's my dream so anyway we're
starting in the I think it's the first
week in
May uh because single demo falls on that
day Saturday is single demile 5th of May
which is one of the independence days of
Mexico and we're going to bring all the
Mexican-American Community we have a lot
of illegals coming through our Retreat
area it's one of the main routes into
the United States because it's mountains
so they hundreds of illegals come
through our land every year many of them
injured uh John Brady had a uh an
illegal with a broken leg he was taking
care of him in his Retreat cabin and
sent him out and we took care of
him and uh we want to take care of them
so anyway we want to make it also a
Haven for people who are desperate and
uh so anyway we're going to make it a
nice big party mirachi bands we're
importing alandro to teach
salsa uh that guadara group is coming up
the next Prescott Retreat winter retreat
will be held in
guadalahara uh because we have too many
of our friends in other countries are
being refused visas like the Argentinian
group I think 12 people were refused
visas only one got through and uh it's
just crazy it's uh barbaric but I we
can't do anything about it so we're
going to move that Retreat to guadara
and it's a beautiful beautiful beautiful
place in the mountain mountains and uh
we had a retreat with 150 people there
last year so we're going to move it the
Winter retreat will be in guara very
beautiful and about the same price okay
because everything's cheaper so anyway
uh we'd like to invite you to come for s
De Mayo it's sort of a new chapter in
diamond mountain and then those of you
who are interested we want to really
make it into a
worldclass resort not Resort retreat
center but
like no I think like really beautiful
cabins and beautiful gardens and
fountains and you know a place where you
would be happy to spend a few weeks and
and we pamper you and we treat you
really special and uh I we'd like to
change the energy from sort of it was an
entrepreneurial energy and now we'd like
to make it more elegant and U so if you
like to help with that come on S with
the okay the thing is here all right we
mixed in Tara with all the okay so uh
please come back at 20 after 10 if you
want to know how it's going to feel in
Nirvana
okay